噉啊！
啊！我又可以開會啦。
二零一九年冠狀病毒。
大家有冇問題？冇意見，OK。
噉啊！我哋而家邀請當局。
機場管理局按計劃推展三跑道系統項目。
病情疫情令到全球航空業嘅經營環境受到嚴重嘅打擊。
嘅副局長同埋機管局三跑項目嘅執行總監揀。
咁議題二，香港國際機場三跑道系統嘅最新發展。
誒主要官員就簡介下香港國際機場三跑，我哋嘅邀請運防局。
噉我想提提大家，如果有需要嗰陣時咧，就誒你發現之前就誒，如果有任何嘅利益申報，就大家首先申報嘅利益。
大家如果要問問題，就要撳先撳掣。噉啊，我預就暫時每個問題四分鐘連問連答。
噉啊，議庭議程議題一，上次至二零二零年五月廿五號嘅會議之後，秘書處局發出咗五份資料文件，文件嘅題目已列於議程上。
咁多謝阿副局。係。噉啊，噉我邀請你哋先簡介下嗰個三跑最新嘅情況。你哋有個嗰個幻燈片。係。噉啊，或者我做個簡單嘅簡介先，畀機管局嘅同事做個presentation啦。
Thank you, thank you, Chairman.
同埋所面對嘅挑戰。
It's the six hundred and fifty hectare reclamation.
Nearly four years now, so we're nearly halfway through the eight-year project.
All of those components, including the APM system and the baggage handling system, are part of this project.
it involves a new third runway passenger building on that new reclamation, which is connected via
有關財務安排最新嘅進展，機管嘅同事找去亦都會為各位嘅議員咧係作介紹。
項目執行總監潘嘉雲先生同埋佢同事簡介三跑道系統項目嘅最新進展。多謝主席。好啊，唔該，潘生。
2.6 kilometres of tunnel, both for APM and baggage handling system, linking it to a new expanded terminal two processing terminal.
五年期嘅銀行貸款，亦都要私募方式向機構投資者發行四批七年期同埋十年期嘅港元債券。
根據機管局嘅估算，三跑道系統嘅建造成本按付款當日價格計算，大約係港幣一千四百一十五億元。
I'm pleased to say that we've made very good progress since we last met. The work has continued from the end of two thousand and sixteen. We've been going.
If I might just remind members, of course, I'm sure they're aware, the 3Rs project at HKA is a significant project comprising many components.
各方自憲者嘅意見，我會繼續定期向立法會同埋各位議員彙報三跑道系統嘅最新進展，並聽取議員嘅意見。主席，我而家有請機管局三跑道。
好啊，唔該。係主席，香港國際機場一直係全球最繁忙嘅機場之一，為咗應付長遠持續增長嘅航空交通量，同埋維持香港得嚟不易嘅航空物流交通樞紐嘅地位，三跑道系統對香港未來嘅發展非常之重要。而特區政府會繼續支持香港。
旅遊同埋商務出行幾乎停頓，疫情亦都對三跑道系統嘅項目個個反巢造成唔同程度嘅影響。儘管係噉樣，英管局仍然迎難而上，繼續依照既定嘅時間表積極進行三跑道系統工程。稍後機管局嘅同事會詳細介紹有關工程嘅進度。
機管局已經批出嘅主要合約價值大約係六百二十六億元咧，維持喺預算之裏邊，並且繼續喺以喺預算一千四百一十五億元裏邊完成整項三跑道系統嘅項目為目標。財務方面為咗維持流動資金嘅水平，機管局而家係同銀行安排一項。
鑑於三跑道系統項目嘅規模、成本同埋複雜程度，公眾期望政府密切監察機管局落實該項目嘅工作同埋進度。我十分明白議員同埋社會大眾喺呢方面嘅關注，亦都認同三跑道系統嘅進展係需要社受到社會同埋立法會嘅監察，並且聽取。
嗯。
is now complete.
到The Follow-on Works。
And I think really the most significant achievement we've achieved since the we last met is.
The red areas are crucial because in the coming months we'll be handing over more remote, more of those areas.
who are progressing now with the follow-on works for the airfield runway and taxiways themselves.
The sea wall, some 13.5 kilometres around the entire perimeter.
And you can see really now the very tangible benefits or results of our reclamation.
The reclamation has proceeded at a considerable pace, and we've now completed nearly seventy per cent of the filling operation.
You can see on the diagram the green and yellow areas. These have been handed over to the airfield works contractors.
I would point, since this was produced for May, further progress has been made, and in fact, other areas have now been handed over in those red areas.
The DCM process, which was new to Hong Kong, has proved to be very successful, and I'm pleased to report there that you'll see that 97% of the marine-based DCM
We've also handed over the orange area to the follow-on works for the terminal passenger building foundation works, which have started on time this year.
With all of those works area handed over now to the main reclamation contractor, we have, as members will remember, some land-based DCM. We're progressing very well with that, and we've now completed some 19, nearly 20% of that.
We've now completed in its core 83% of the seawall. The core is important because that allows us to properly form the reclamation behind it. There is still some work on the on the seawalls to be done in the final finishing.
Members will be aware that there were some problems with the early stages in the fill materials for this reclamation, and so we phased the reclamation to enable timely handover to the follow-on contractors to ensure that the reclamation is filled to meet our schedule.
背景。
嗯。
That's been done on time.
The runway in two thousand and twenty-two.
Some of the areas now being handed over in that area.
foundations of of significant buildings necessary for the operation of the
There's also been significant tunnel works leading towards new reclamation.
station for the new terminal two, and also for the the underground baggage hall for the baggage handling system.
The much-needed substructure and foundation works, which we which we awarded earlier this year, and so those works have now commenced.
I'm pleased to say that in addition to the reclamation, we've also been building at a pace on the existing island in the vicinity of Terminal Two.
transfer all of the control systems for the existing T1 into that building to allow us to better rectify and renovate and change Terminal Two building.
在北面的區域，現在有相當大的基礎工程已經完成，打樁和隔牆，我們現在開始挖掘地下的地庫，這將是為APM
You can see there the footprint in blue of the the larger terminal two, and to the left, top left, this is the south annex building. Building now has achieved OP. This is crucial for enabling us to.
You can see here a photograph from the east, which is the easiest way to get a view. So we're looking down the length of the runway here, and you can see from the east right the way through into the distance that a large majority of that reclamation is finished. In fact.
Here is a view of the footprint of the third runway passenger building. You can see there a very considerable amount of reclamation has been completed. That's important because although not necessary for 2022, it will be ready for 2024, and therefore we must start the
This is the in the extreme western area. This is the beginnings of the support buildings necessary for the runway, including the construction support areas. We will have concrete batching plants, asphalt batching plants, all of the necessary infrastructure to to to enable those works. And you can see there the very considerable and the.
with those species in the surrounding areas.
which is the highest Hong Kong beam category for buildings.
It's important also that the marine ecology. We're very aware.
We also look for opportunities where we can do more going forward.
The MTR line, which you'll see in the bottom left corner.
So we continue to work on the island, and as I say, we're making good progress.
Making very careful to ensure that the species that we're releasing are consistent.
Including a lot of the advance works necessary to allow us to now shortly start building the tunnel underneath the.
colonisation of various species on the existing seaward. Of course, a great part of the sea will be rock.
rubble, which again has has a very good impact in terms of providing habitat for some of the smaller species.
We're also doing a number of aspects, including fish restocking pilot test. We've released over 8,000 black seabream, yellowfish, seabream and green groupers.
scientific advisers that we've now managed to transplant over 500 pieces of coral and and those are are thriving with a mortality rate very very successful at the moment. We continue to monitor those and hope that we can learn.
We also for the civil works, we're doing a considerable amount of civil works, so we we're using a an international recognised system called CQUAL, which allows us to grade, and we've achieved an excellent grading for our civils works in terms of how we're conducting those.
A few updates, very briefly on the environmental aspects. We are continuing to strive for excellence in environment in the design. I'm pleased to say we've achieved a platinum rating for the initial platinum rating for the design of terminal two, and those works will go on, and we're confident of achieving that platinum.
跟住落嚟咧，就由我誒。
The construction of the runway now now ongoing.
場誒零售投資者去認購嘅。
As you can see, there, this is we're about.
And we shortly be doing a pilot test on those.
They're also doing looking at the Chinese white dolphin conservation in the in the cross the whole of the PRD.
update大家將關於我哋嘅財務安排啦。咁喺二零二一年度咧，我哋嘅融資安排咧就誒。
Along the centre line of what will be the future runway, with the two taxiways parallel, taxiways will be to the areas to the left.
噉我哋個原本嘅計劃咧，就會喺二零二零年嘅第一季去推出，畀市場嘅誒零售投資者咧去認購嘅。
For future projects for the future, as to how better to do that, we're also exploring the possibility of using artificial reefs in the area.
有幾方面做咗嘅。我哋原本咧就應該喺一九二零年嘅財政年度咧就會有一隻零售債券推出，咁個銀碼咧就係五十億港元嘅定息嘅。
Before I pass on to my colleague on the finance side, I'd just like to just perhaps show, if you may, a short video which shows a line of the reclamation to give a scale of the of the work that's been done. We're flying roughly from west to east.
We're also looking at other aspects, and these are all being done by local institutions and NGOs looking at the various species. So we've seen examples there of some of them, the sustainable aquaculture, and also looking at the impact of microplastics on Chinese horseshoe crabs.
of the reclamation, which will has an impact on the the environment, and so therefore we've been looking at part of that reclamation, where we we're hoping to encourage the return of species by having an echo enhancement seawall. We've got over 500 echo enhanced seawall blocks, which will allow and promote
We've also done, in addition to the translocation of coral, we've also conducted a very large scale coral trial transportate where we actually transplanted. This is cutting the coral, which had not been done very successfully previously before. I'm pleased to say that working with our
In terms of other environmental aspects, we of course have supported through a fund setting up an independent fund for enhancement of the ecology and also support of the fishermen in the area. We continue to monitor the Chinese white dolphin very closely, and we're through this scheme.
銀行貸款嘅。
咁誒。
噉，按財務方面咧，就係咁多。
時咁聽到有白海豚嘅屍體發現。
定息、定期貸款同埋一個銀行循環貸款。
下一個中期嚟講咧，就會隨時準備我哋咧可以出一啲譬如誒綠色債券噉樣嘅。
咁所以咧，我哋而家咧誒基金局咧就會誒將嗰個誒融資嘅規模咧就加大嘅。
咁誒初步嚟講，我哋同啲銀行傾談嘅時候咧，誒銀行嘅反應係非常良好嘅，噉佢哋都好支持我哋嘅項目。
咁喺呢個零售債券嘅停滯之後咧，我哋就同銀行咧就誒開始商談，關於我哋安排一個二百億港元嘅五年期嘅。
咁誒，至於個其他嘅，譬如細節，譬如誒，都係一個五年期啦。咁至於其他細節，譬如息率啊，誒參與嘅銀行嗰啲咧，我哋融後咧就會有公佈㗎啦。
係個報告係咁多，暫時係嘛。O.K.唔該。咁為咗開放畀委員發問題嘅時間，咁第一位係毛孟靜議員，跟住嘅探問好啲長嘅，請問。
咁至於個時間啊，或者詳細嘅情況咧，我哋就要睇翻誒幾樣嘢啦，包括我哋本身嘅現金水平啦，我哋嘅貸款嘅需求啦，三跑道嘅誒進行嘅情況啦，同埋最緊要咧，我諗係個市場嘅情況。咁咧之後咧，我哋就會先至再作決定嘅。
third of the way along the runway on the right there will be the area that will take the taxiways back towards the existing airport. You can see in the top right the large footprint which will be the area for the third runway building. And where all of the land beneath us on this drone flight taken in May is showing the reclamation that is will be used for.
但係隨住二月嘅時候啦，新冠肺炎嘅爆發啦，噉我哋自己誒內部作咗一個評估啦，認為當時咧唔係一個適當嘅時候推出，所以咧我哋就會將呢一個零售債券嘅計劃咧推遲，但係仍然預計咧會喺二零二一年度嘅財政年度裏邊咧係推出畀市。
如果大家睇翻呢一個誒時間表咧，我哋嘅執行時間表咧，其實我哋都圈咗咧，就係原本我哋諗住發行嘅零售債券就誒褪遲咗啦，就褪遲咗一年啦。而我哋而家做緊嘅咧，就係紅色框裏邊嘅銀行貸款同埋誒嗰個誒refunding credit facility，即係循環。
咁至於咧中期嚟講咧，我哋就而家籌組緊一個綠色誒融資嘅框架。咁因為而家市場上對於綠色、綠色嘅融誒金融咧比較有興趣啦。咁亦都我哋覺得咧，因為我哋基金局咧睇誒綠色嘅環保方面咧做咗唔少嘅功夫，所以我哋咧就。
四分鐘啊！唔該曬，就誒喺今時今日咧，我哋見到赤立國水正河飛，你又同我哋講三跑誒，呢個真係有少少哭笑不得噉。但係希望誒啲其他啲誒情況嚇會一路好轉啦。就亦都係不。
但係呢個真係講嚟講去，我講咗八年，我都誒冇心機啦，咪算啦嚇。我同你講融資嘅問題，我就係有誒少少擔心咧。你哋首先就嗰個零售債券，因為市場情況不理想啊嘛，就要延遲到明年啦。咁然後你係銀行貸。
係。
係咪啊，吳生？好啊，唔該。
好，阿邊位係咪吳生回應，定係局長回應？
誒，啲咪係咪唔得？但係其實，
噉樣誒啲錢係噉樣誒呢頭嗰頭噉。
做任何嘅支援或者補貼，咁而家係請誒基本嘅同事咧做個補充。
款你就講二百億，但係可以最高去到三百億嘅，好明顯係嘛？
誒，我諗喺誒正話所提到嘅誒財務報告裏邊咧，已經因應咗唔同嘅環境咧，有作出誒決定嘅。咁誒，亦都誒。
冇啦，咁喺度傾嘅時候咧，大家都覺得咧，佢哋本身銀行都會覺得咧，即係而家嘅情況咧係一個好短暫，或者係一個誒。
一個唔覺意就真係誒負債太多嘅情況太壞，仍然要係公堂打救，又係另一個海洋公園，會唔會咧？
突然之間嘅嘅場狀況嘅啫，唔會係一個永久持續嘅。如果唔係嘅話，佢哋可能對於個信貸都未必會咁容易就去支持我哋啦。咁所以對於呢一方面咧，誒，我哋都比較有信心嘅。
啊！我想知嘅係啊機場基本局而家目前嘅收支或者係負債情況。第一，啊，我想加多一句就係你將來嗰個啊機場附加税係咪應該會褪後嘅咧？都
而家個財嗰個財務情況同埋嗰個機場誒，應該旅客嗰個機場税係係係嘛？咁而家呢段時間梗係冇曬旅客啦，你嗰個會損失一個好大嘅收入嘅嗰個情況係點？
我就擔心喺而家噉樣嘅一個經濟環境，香港嘅誒外來投資者嘅信心又受到好大嘅政治因素嘅衝擊。我想知而家機管局嘅收資或者係負債嘅情況係點？因為我好擔心咧誒，如果機管局係一路噉。
我首先做個簡單回應先啦。基金局嗰個財務顧問咧係以共同承擔、農者自負嘅原則咧，係就第三跑道系統嗰個整體嘅財務安排嘅。咁透透過咧三個途徑為項目籌集資金。咁基金會係會按計劃咧係為三跑道系統咧係進行融資嘅。目前政府喺財政上邊咧係唔需要為三跑道係。
嚟到畀我哋嗰個詳細嘅財務報告啦。噉我諗誒嗱誒事態嘅發展咧，我會覺得咧誒隨住市場嘅慢慢回復翻嚟咧，我我哋都有幾有信心咧，我哋嘅財務狀況咧會一路噉樣去改善嘅。噉我諗咧誒，亦都喺我哋同銀行商討嘅時候，呢一個係一個五年嘅債。
啊！
可以咩？
係邊位？
係仍然一粒海沙都冇交過落嚟，係咪啊？
算即係改變呢一樣嘢字啊！多謝主席。誒，譚文豪議員。
空域，關於空域嘅問題，好啊。主席或者等我回答。係啊，楊楊小姐。
個主席誒，第一個問題咧就係成份文件咧都冇講過空域嗰個問題嘅，而家究竟同大陸傾個空域搞成點啊？唔該。
女士，可唔可以重複多謝？誒，如果嗰個你哋同大灣區同埋國內草嶺島嗰個合作。
嗰個文本可唔可以交嚟立法會畀我哋？你話下半年預計下半年有啊嘛，因為嚇呢一個問題其實誒，我哋以往都有提及過啦，就係關於康域呢一個咧，其實因為參與嗰個誒。
標咁三方小組咧，就係我哋以往喺委員會都同各位誒議員交代過，而家咧就做緊一個關於大灣區空域嘅類比模擬工作。噉我哋預計咧喺今年下半年咧就會有一個初步嘅結果。
而初步結果咧出咗之後咧，佢哋會再做一個詳細研究，希望咧制定一啲具體嘅措施，可以進一步咧優化空域嘅管理同埋交通嘅管理。O.K.，唔該，我想請問咧，下半年出咗呢一個嘅誒誒草議嘅時候，可唔可以交一份去誒立法會？
誒除咗香港之外，仲有國家民航局同埋澳門民航局，咁入邊亦都咧涉及一啲比較敏感嘅資料。噉我哋咧其實政府咧以往喺一啲誒重要嘅決定有之後咧，我哋都會出一啲新聞稿。但係自己個文本嗰度咧，我哋相信誒現階段我哋應該都咁咁或者唔係成個文本交上嚟咯，但係係一個撮要啦，起碼可唔可以啊？
或或者誒主席，我答一答先咧。關於嗰個誒機場建設費用ACF，咁其實就一路響誒機場嗰個即係融資開頭個方案咧，都已經咧就係話佢哋大約咧誒會係收到所有嘅負債還清為止，而當時嘅股選咧就係話收到二零三零三一。
一嗰個嘅財政年度，咁但係暫時嚟講咧，因為誒呢個即係新冠病毒病個疫情嘅影響咧，其實就誒嗰個完全個情況咧，而家都係難以一時間咧完全能夠即係解釋得到嘅，即係或者能夠做到所有嘅誒評估啊。咁但係而家暫時嚟講，基金局都未有打。
誒銀行署咧一路都係同緊國家銀行局同埋澳門銀行局嗰度咧，組成咗個三方小組，佢哋喺度研究同埋落實緊咧各項優化咧珠三角空域嘅措施，咁希望可以透過一個循序漸進嘅方式咧，達到香港國際機場可以每小時處理一百零二班呢一個航班嘅長遠目。
我哋會翻去同其他參與方再研究一下先。噉，但係我哋而家目前嗰個做法咧，都係按以往嗰個安排，就係定時咧將一啲主要嘅資訊咧透過一個新聞稿嘅方式發佈畀大家。多謝主席。嗱，另外一個問題咧，關於海沙嘅誒，我而家睇到咧就係我可唔可以確認一樣嘢？而家喺廣東省。
嗯。
我未。
係唔該，主席。誒，我有兩方面問題嘅，一方面就關於錢啦。
You're right. We have had a considerable amount of sand from Guangdong.
追討翻啊！唔該，係機委會誒，或者請機管嘅同事做個補充呢方面。好啊。
Thank you. Can I just point out that from last year, remember we were some
18 weeks behind and and obviously pushing and we came up a number of plans then as to how we would recover that time. I'm pleased to say that we have recovered that.
咁五月嘅時候咧，報紙已經賣啦，就係你個填海嗰部分咧，就超支咗八十億。不過機管局咧就話，一四一五嗰個總額就不變嘅。
To date, it has been our largest supply. That Guangdong sand has been from customised sand, and more recently we've been getting marine sand from from Guangdong. We've also been getting sand from Guangxi.
噉我信住你先啦。噉我就想問翻，因為而家你今日畀我哋嗰個誒融資借錢嗰部分咧，其實你誒嗰個總額啊，已經係講到係。
嗯，and we continue to manage our projects with up in a normal project management style, with all our contractors following up as necessary any conditions that we need to to impose。珠海地議員。
We've gone from eighteen weeks now to just six weeks behind. Even with the impact of COVID, that is. Otherwise, we would have done a little better. That is a result of very hard work working with our contractor to supply a diverse range of sands.
係啲咪？誒或者補充少少啦。其實咧，我哋喺廣東省政府咧已經喺二零一九年七月咧係完成咗掛牌出讓三個沙源工作，而基於個主要嘅填海工程嘅承建商一直係同呢個中標嘅供應商咧合談。喺二零二零年嘅五月咧，已經係從呢個位於湛江嘅沙源咧開始進行開沙。
而且會持續供應海沙畀呢個填海工程，即係開始供應海沙啦。嗱好啦，咁但係咧，你之前咧就因為佢畀唔到海沙啦，所以你要用呢一個機沙，甚至乎咧係增加更加多嘅地方用你個D C M，即係話深層誒水泥攪拌個方法嚟到做。咁呢啲額外嘅支出，你會唔會問翻當日嘅承辦商嚟到？
嘅。
用咧，第一個問題啦，呢個。
五百五十億至到。
大陸嘅運沙船咧，係去咗佢哋嘅海域。
總值咧係十五億港元嘅，噉佢。
基本上咧有一個誒指控嘅，就叫有間公司就叫九州之星。
就去非法去盜沙，噉佢哋已經計咗嗰個數啦，就係話起碼有五百萬立方米。
第二個問題咧就係誒關於誒海沙嘅採沙嘅或者填料嘅，咁喺文件裏面咧就第六段提到。
咁呢個就喺台灣已經賣到行曬，但係我其實一月嘅時候，我見到機管局有有一個答案就話，誒會確保嗰啲境外嘅海沙係合法啦噉樣。
啲合法嘅出口證，譬如馬來西亞或者菲律賓咁啱你第六段boy又寫馬來西亞、菲律賓，佢哋就指控，而家台灣嘅傳媒就指控你，就係借住大陸公司就。
just fill in my question. My question was, you increase the amount or the the the the money that you throw into the DCM because due to the lack of the the marine sands, for that extra cost of money, are you going to ask the contractor for any compromise? We have been working with our contractor all the way through. We've refazed the we've.
made a number of changes to the reclamation to recover that programme to get us back on target for two thousand and twenty-two and twenty-four. With that, we've done a number of phase as you write. We've done more DCM. That is both to our advantage in terms of phasing, but also in terms of the long-term settlement of those things. So there are other technical advantages of using DCM.
七百八十億港元嗱，呢個已經係多過你喺一路以嚟咧同我哋講嗰個分配啊，即係話六百九十億就借錢，二百六十億就係基層建設費，四百七十億就係營運嘅盈餘。我想問呢一個喺一五年一路。
舉到而家嘅呢一個融資嘅分配係唔係仲適用嘅咧？因為你好明顯睇到機場建設費嗰個部分咧，你而家冇啦。跟住左邊呢一個營運盈餘又唔知你跌咗幾多，咁呢一個噉嘅pie係咪繼續適？
其他填料咧就有誒嚟自台灣嘅，噉我唔知呢啲填料係咩意思，係唔係即係海沙？因為咧喺過去由一月到到誒五月咧，主席台灣嘅傳媒咧係多次噉樣報導咧，係有大陸。
咁但係而家誒就有個台灣嗰邊就好明顯誒，就話唔係噉樣喎。機三跑係用緊一啲非法盜挖嘅沙喺佢哋海域，並且咧係有啲沙咧就挖咗出嚟之後咧，又用一啲方法就去誒迂迴地攞到啲。
攞啲假嘅菲律賓同馬來西亞嘅出口證，就去去攞台灣嘅沙嚟香港。噉我就想誒請局方或者經管局都去澄清翻，或者你會唔會有調查咯？搞到咁多個月都好啊。誒邊個或者多謝朱華迪議員嘅提問先，或者我首先就重申翻政府一個嘅。
觀點，跟住先畀翻經管同事咧，就解釋翻佢個填料同埋嗰個嘅誒預算嗰個問題。一如其他嘅運送到港嗰啲物料咧，相關部門咧都會按既定嘅程序同埋需要咧，係輸入嘅填料咧係申報個文件係進行抽查嘅。根根據運防局嘅瞭解咧，經管局咧一直都係。
用嘅。
呃，感染，係啊。
And question number three.
If we have exceeded the budget.
誒多謝主席。誒關於嗰個誒。
咁至於人哋台灣話你係誒倒挖嗰度啲沙，噉你有咩回應？有有冇補充回應？
And it certainly did not apply to our contractor. We check the the location and where the sanders come from for all of our materials. The materials arriving from
係要遵守嘅，兼工同事可以就喺多方面做個補充。係邊位補充？第一個問題就係嗰個誒收資收資嗰個派嘅問題啊，阿吳生。
Does the expenditure on reclamation work along? I'm only asking the expenditure on reclamation work commensurate with the percentage completed so far. If not, how much have we exceeded the budget?
東出佢嘅主要嘅填海嘅承建商喺採購填料嗰陣咧，係務必遵守香港同埋嘅嘅填料來源地嘅相關。主席可唔可以具體答呢個？人哋台灣指控你，你係咪否認先？我或者喺呢方面咧，強調咧就係我哋係會就係根據個工程嘅需求咧，係做一個相關嘅法例同埋守則。
經費嘅來源嗰度啦，我諗啊，議員提問嘅就關於個派嗰度啦。嗰個數目字咧，其實我哋而家仲係適用嘅，因為嗰個咧就係基本上由我哋嘅財務顧問去提供嘅。咁但係當然啦，我哋誒監管局咧就會繼續保持警覺，去監睇下市場嘅變化啦。咁但係而家嚟講咧，嗰個派差仍然係適用。
Yes, can I answer that directly? We have sand from a number of areas, including the Philippines and Malaysia, but not, I'd say, at the moment because of COVID, that's been closed down. We very carefully check the credentials of all of the sand coming to us. We are aware of that media report, and I can tell you that we looked into.
從台灣，是個processed dredged material， and so we're very very happy that we we're sure that all the material getting is from legitimate purposes. We we we will issue a statement to clarify this report。主要地理員，你撳咗第二輪，你第二輪先撳，首先再問個大家。
啊！如果因為時間問題，我如果冇乜，大家委員再撳掣，我喺度畫線先。跟住有梁繼昌議員。啊，主席，我想睇翻嗰個slide啊，number two about the reclamation progress。I mean the chart shows the various components of the reclamation process， and I I do believe
here is that the percentage completion ranges from 97% to 19%. I have three questions. Number one, does it mean that the whole reclamation process, if the figures shown on the right in the right column reach, you know, 100%, that's my first question. And the second quest
What measures have been put in place to control the cost of reclamation? Because I do think this is really the most sizeable amount of expenditure in the whole process. And I also have a another question on financing。嗱，我喺誒嗰個誒融資嗰個。
beneath that.
嗯。
We have to build a rock core.
In those areas, is now ninety-seven percent complete under the whole platform.
用deep cement mixing to solidify the the softer materials, the muds, which all remained in place.
That has to be carried out before the reclamation can carry on above it, which is why it's very significant that the marine-based DCM.
The seawall, as I said, is 13.5 kilometres in total length around, which actually is longer than the the built seawall on the existing airport.
亦起碼你你同我商業銀行貸款都應該要要要差唔多嗰個數量。我唔知點解嗰個考慮係乜嘢？係咪你驚誒個市場太差冇人買？
其實香港好多市民都可能有興趣買嘅，噉我唔知你嗰個retail bond係針對嘅係機機構投資者啊，抑或一般嘅散户投資者？好，唔該曬四條題目，唔該。誒，投邊邊位啊，阿鄭生。
問題咧就其實就好簡單，或者都唔係簡單嘅。你睇翻嗰個融資嗰個detail funding plan and indicative implementation time timeline嗰個誒嗰個圖啊，即係喺個financial arrangement嘅第第二幅圖嗰度。
The land-based DCM can then will be done once the reclamation is up at the required level. So that's something that follows on later. It's less critical and is in areas that are are not critical to areas of of the main works that are carrying on.
其中有一個就係誒retail bonds，咁大概係會有五十億咧，同埋嗰個商業嘅銀行貸款就大概係二百億至三百億中間。嗱，我我想問嘅問題係點解嗰個分配係噉樣樣？點解會嗰個商業嘅銀行貸款銀團嘅？
泰塊係多過誒呢一個retail bonds嗱？點解我咁問咧？因為其實呢個retail bonds對我哋香港嗰個啊Hong Kong dollar嘅債券市場係有好大嘅提升作用。我唔明白點解誒機管局喺做呢一個融資嘅安排時咁保守，只係畀五十。
Chairman, if I may, then I'll answer the first part on the the reclamation, the slide, the reclamation progress. Thank you for your questions on that. Let me let me elaborate. I jumped over it perhaps a little quick. The reclamation comprises many parts. Underneath a large proportion, over half of the area of the reclamation, we have.
And then the reclamation can be built behind it. So 83% of that, over 12 kilometres, have now been complete. The small piece that hasn't been completed is the area to the extreme west that wraps around. Just go onto the cost side because I'm more concerned about the cost. In terms of cost, I'd like to emphasise then that to date the project project estimates remain
within the original budget, one for one five, and I can tell you that that also applies. That we're within the total budget allocation for the reclamation works as well. So we don't have an overspend. So I hope that helps you. We're within budget, and we continue to diligently manage the budget and the project very carefully. Well, Canton.
成本咧，唔該主席。
financing嘅問題。
各位陳振英議員，誒唔該主席。
噉啊，一對外發債，其實時機係好差嘅。
But when that's now behind us, and we're now focused fully on making sure that in the coming year, we expect to recover that six weeks.
噉我相信咧，即係成本應該會比佢原先估計誒高好多。但係我想誒問下咧，而家有冇評估過咧幾種嘅融資方式咧？喺而家嘅情況之下咧，邊種嘅融資方式成本係最低嘅？
What we have done is refased some of the reclamation works to make sure that we focus on the areas that are critical. First of all, to do the areas that need to be ready for 2022, and we're largely on the way with that. And then there are other areas outside that which
好啊，邊咪負盈餘？Okay, I will. Thank you very much. You're right. This time last year, I was fully transparent, and we were obviously disappointed to declare that we were slipping behind because of the very real difficulties we had with the film materials.
materials， so that we can be sure that we can deliver our programme. We haven't， and I can understand the concern is we haven't fiddled the programme. We we are sticking with our original programme of course， and we are on programme to deliver our 2022 and confident of achieving 2022 and 2024.
第一個問題好簡單，我想問下，頭先啊吳總監都提到啦，就話填海工程進度咧，原先有十八個禮拜嘅滯後嘅，但係逐漸咧縮縮短到咧近期得翻六個星期。咁但係喺文件又提到咧，係因為係唔係因為呢樣嘢咧？我想問下咧，就積極重整個時間表，重新編定呢個施工。
優先次序同埋調整填海工程嘅設計，噉係咪真係用咗呢幾個方法咧？就係誒掩蓋咗咧，即係其實滯後嗰個問題咧。咁呢個第一個問題，第二個問題都係關於誒融資嘅，因為若航空業而家面對嗰個困難咧，我覺得誒機管局又要喺短時間內咧決定咧做一啲銀行貸款。
如果係有一種係零息低嘅咧，噉我想問下啦。咁成個融資嘅組合啊，你會唔會因應有一啲係低啲，咁將呢個組合咧重新編配過？噉啊，第三樣嘢咧就係其實應該係利息貴咗嘅。咁呢個利息嘅上升咧，會唔會影響到成個三跑道項目嘅總成？
But I'm very pleased to say, obviously that was a result of a greater highly competitive demand for film materials at that time. In the intervening year since we last met, we have made considerable effort with our contractors. We promised to do to secure adequate supply of suitable materials from multiple sources, and the importance was making sure we had a diverse source of
As the time passes, become more critical, and so we're focusing on those as well. So I'm pleased to say that we brought the eighteen weeks slip down. It's down to just six weeks delay, and that's having over. We had some problems, obviously, as you can imagine, in February March with COVID, which stopped the supply for a period. So I'm pleased to say we would have done better if not for that.
英國嘅。
我我噉樣。
八角嘅啦。
機動快線啦，我亦都有申報。
咁跟住係姚思榮議員。
呢個舒緩措施同埋個收入又係收入嘅問題，個現金流嘅問題。
支援措施，如果有嘅話，呢個預算你哋做好準備未咧？好啊，邊位邊位回應？
誒三跑嘅開支喺誒第一個問題係個資金流方面，你哋誒會點？誒即係預算冇問題，但係資金流方面你有冇大有問有問題咧？
哦，好啊，唔該，唔該，六位國議員。好啊，姚思榮議員。多謝主席。我先申報咧，我哋公司係誒機場入面嘅租户，誒有我哋有其他業務喺度，亦係誒提供一啲中轉服務嘅。
誒另外就係誒去到咩程有冇預計去到咩程度咧？你哋嘅財務會出現一個危機。即係而家你哋可能話冇問題啦，但係七八月我哋估計都係復甦，都誒會有個過程。咁去咩情況你哋會出現危機？
延延遲嘅時候咧，我哋已經立即同銀行去傾談㗎啦。咁誒，亦都同一時間咧，我哋傾談亦都講咗啦。誒，所以咧就可能會將二百億嗰個銀碼咧增解。咁所以其實主要原因咧就係令到我哋咧有充足嘅現金流咧去應付誒見到誒嘅情況嘅嚇。唔該。
誒財務問題係嘛，林生？多謝主席。誒，我諗整體嚟講咧，而家其實全球嘅經濟嚟講咧，誒比較慢啦。咁所以息口咧，其實係同幾年前比咧係下跌咗好多嘅。咁誒當然啦，誒因為隨住誒整體經濟嘅差咧，對部分嘅公司嚟講咧，佢嘅借貸成本係增加咗。但係因為機管局。
本身嘅送貸咧，仍然係比較高嘅，咁所以對於我哋嚟講咧，個借貸息口咧就冇特別嘅上升度嘅。咁至於誒正亞議員提到嘅，會唔會話編排一下誒唔同，淨係借誒最平嗰種嘅誒工具咧？噉我諗，因為我哋借貸嘅銀碼咧比較大，咁同埋咧我哋亦都要分開咧喺唔同嘅。
年期去誒誒誒，即係唔同嘅年期到期嘅，因為我哋唔可以將所有嘢咧都淨係做一樣。咁如淨係做一樣嘅話咧，嗰個利息成本咧慢慢其實係會增加嘅。咁所以咧，我哋都會跟翻誒誒匯豐誒幫我哋做嘅財務報告啦。噉我哋都會喺唔同嘅誒工具，亦都唔同嘅年期去做嘅。嚇，多謝主席。
咁誒就有關誒呢個大家知道啦，由呢個三月十七號誒香港發出紅色警示到同埋廿五號咧，誒機場嘅中轉服務誒暫停，誒對誒成個誒旅遊業啦或者係機場入面嗰個營運咧，帶嚟到好好大影響。噉你好多謝。
機管局咧就係誒撥出咗四十六億嘅舒緩嘅一啲嘅措施啦嚇，咁使到航空公司啊租户咧唔使承擔咁重嘅開支嚇。咁但係始終嚟講咧，頭先講都係嗰個預算啦啊誒，一方面就冇咗收入，另一方面你哋要誒支措好大量嘅開支，包括誒。
第二個問題就係有關誒，就係誒七，我知你七八月咧，你哋已經係誒對一啲租户都採取一個減免嘅做法，誒係咪包包喺四十六億入面咧？嚇誒，如果係七八月嘅情況並冇改善，你哋有冇準備下一階段嘅？
誒多謝主席，我諗我答咗現金流嗰個部分先啦。誒嗱誒，基本局咧就基本上咧，我哋嘅現金流都比較充富裕嘅。噉我亦都知道咧，我哋嚟緊咧有一個比較誒一個大嘅三炮工程啦，同埋我哋本身嘅日常誒支出啦。所以喺方嗰方面咧，所以今年我哋當我哋個零售債券
社會事件之言計啊！
個現金流或者個財政會有問題啊！
啊，係唔該，主席。我想問啊，點解今日林天福主席唔嚟嘅？
誒正話回應咗係冇超支，亦冇話過會延期。
有冇人回應啊？點啊？阿林天福行政總裁，噉佢唔係主席，應該。
已經答不曬啲問題啊！應該是第一樣嘢啦，係咪？噉啊，我我當係後邊嗰樣嘢啦，係嘛？
我我想問問咧，即係而家應該對上一次會，我哋講過，應該你哋而家係冇超支、冇延期啊嘛，係嘛？
疫情嘅時間計啊，定係喺之前，定係之後計啊？你計邊條數㗎？因為啲人而而家啲人數話其實。
即係主席，我諗而家嚟講咧，誒去講呢個誒危機咧比較言之尚早，因為我哋本身嘅誒資金咧而家都比較充裕嘅，咁嚟緊短時間誒中長期時間內咧，我哋都有足夠嘅資金去支付嘅。O K，好啊，阿邵家輝議員。
啊工程啦，係咪咁？你而家去融資啦，係咪？我我想問你哋融資咧，你預嗰條數嘅時候咧，嗯，你都要講畀人聽。其實你有幾錢收入㗎嘛？係咪咁？啲收入就係計嗰啲人頭税啦，係咪咁？即係計有幾多人嚟香港同埋離開香港，係咪？你計嗰條數話係喺。
好，跟住阿鄭生。至於支援措施嗰度咧，就據我瞭解咧，嗰個係誒過往一段時間個四十六億嘅支援措施嚟嘅。咁誒未來嗰段時間咧，我諗我哋誒會緊密留意呢個航空業界嘅發展，先至會再商討商討下一步嘅工作。啊，多謝主席。阿阿處第一問題冇問我，即係你哋。
誒未回回覆，我就係有關嗰個財務誒去到咩情況，你會出現危機，即係話而家我哋都唔知道個疫情去到誒咩程度啊嘛？係咪呢方面做好預計未咧？噉樣另外支援措施方面，我想問下係政府主導即係支援措施，定係機管局同政府係磋商個支援措？
措施，因為咧好多時咧，我哋誒業界追嘅時候咧，政府咧就會話啊睇機管局，經會又話睇政府態度喺呢方面。你哋喺下一階段，如果係有支援措施嘅時候，你哋會邊個去主導咧？我希望政府樓主導呢件事情。係邊位啊？鄭生回應係邊位主導或者副局回應政府同？
基本局咧係同埋啲啲業務夥伴咧同埋持份者係保持呢個嘅緊密嘅接觸嘅，會繼續密切咧係咪留意經濟狀況同埋業界嗰個情況咧，即時咧係檢視我哋嘅措施，盡力咧係協助業界咧喺度過艱難嘅時間嘅。係，阿吳生有冇預計過即係去到咩情況？你哋嗰
有有冇邊個會？呢個會唔重要係嘛，主席？我我喺呢個啊疫情嘅時間，我真係約機管局，即係同啲零售業界，即係希望見佢，即係講下減租嗰啲啦，係咪？噉佢可能忙唔見我哋啦。今日呢個會講緊你三跑上嚟立法會，噉佢都唔使嚟，佢好忙係嘛？定係其實你坐喺度嗰啲人？
係嘛係係嘛。O.K.好就啊！我聽到有啲融資嗰啲情況啦，係咪？因為佢哋誒唔需要經過立法會撥款啦，係咪？噉你哋誒即係借我哋畀咗個權佢收嗰啲叫人頭税係嘛？即係嗰啲空運即係入嚟香港嘅時候收你税啦。噉啊，我哋自己去填補呢個誒，即係起機場嘅。
咁而家。
考慮嘅，做唔到咁點啊？
係邊位回答？
咁如果假設你唔係延長嘅？
嗱，我知㗎啦，得呢個時間唔係好多啊，唔好意思啊。
同以前已經爭好遠啦！唔好講緊疫情啦，講緊喺社會事件嘅時候，你用邊度數計？
噉你啲人頭税，佢呢個機場建設費啦，其實嗰個數，你會唔會加佢哋嘅會？
做唔到嘅話，如果好似海洋公園咁點啊？你又翻過嚟叫香港政府找條數先，到時候你哋都唔係錯曬喺度啦。
咁至於話會唔會延長或者增加個人馬咧？喺現階段咧，機管局咧係冇呢個意思嘅。
喺社會事件嘅時候，啲油價好似唔係上升下降嘅。噉你還款嘅時間，你覺得你會係延長啊，定係會縮短，定係一樣？
咁如果到時候，如果人數你計嘅時候，一七年嘅時候咁多人，跟住你見到社會事件跌咗好多遊客啦，係咪少咗十幾廿percent遊客？咁嗰條數你唔係延長，你又唔係加款，噉你諗你點啊？等於唔還啊？你唔係想辦海洋公園係嘛？
係邊位回答啊？吳生誒，多謝主席。我諗誒，睇翻匯豐嗰陣時，作為財務顧問做嘅時候咧，係二零一五年同埋二零一七年都分別做過個誒報告嘅。噉佢裏邊用嘅數目字咧，基本上咧就誒，首先第一樣嘢咧，我哋而家收嗰個咧就唔係人頭税，係叫做機場建設費。
噉就係離開香港嘅乘客咧，佢要支付嘅。咁嗰陣時咧，誒傾談嘅時候，個財務安排咧就係用者自負嘅原則。基本上咧，即係用機場嘅人咧就要誒承擔嗰個投資誒建機場嘅三跑嘅。二零一五年嘅時間計啊，係咪啊，先生？係嘛？二零一五年嘅時候。同埋二零一七年嘅時間計嗰啲人頭係嘛？得。
係邊位回答啊？吳生係誒，多謝主席。喺而家嘅情況嚟講咧，我哋密切注意個事態發展。咁而家嚟講咧，我哋係仍然好似正話答誒另一位議員咁咧，我哋係base on個仍然existing嗰個pie chart嚟到做嘅。咁當中咧誒，機場建設費咧係有佢嘅貢獻嘅佔比。
你咪代你代表林天福講，你講乜我聽啊！啊，鄭生啊，到時定係定係到時候走嚟叫我哋還，叫我哋幫佢找條數先。誒嗱，我我諗我哋嗰個情況之外，我都解釋過啦，就係話嗰個機場建設費，而嗰個誒即係收嘅時間咧，我哋一開初嘅時候，即係一五年、一六年嘅時候已經定咗咧，就係話大約。
for the reclamation as well.
係，啲咪會型，誒。
所以working very closely with our contractor over the year, we've done that.
可唔可以提供多啲資料，有關呢啲環保嘅要求？
We we continue to work with him to make sure he delivers on time this year.
你哋有冇諗啊？而家現任嘅現任嘅行政總裁，你有冇諗㗎？有冇啲有冇啲有啲乜計劃㗎？
By having come from those diversity sources, obviously we've had to work with a contractor to make sure that he's been able to deliver those materials, and.
嚇，即係誒，若若恕恕我無知啦，係咪？即係呢啲係咪確保第日填到出嚟個跑道咧係冇環保污染咧？係嘛？個作用應該係噉樣啦，係咪？有邊位想補充啊？係咪啊？你你仲喺度啊？
啊，即係唔污染啊噉，咁呢啲係招標時候講明啊，定係之後加入去誒，定係嗰個價錢點樣個點樣計法咧嚇？即係嗰啲有冇考慮過嗰啲承辦商要點樣應付呢個問題？佢哋實在做唔做得到咧？
簡單回應埋阿蘇繼輝呢個問啊，其實就即係啊，機管局會一路因應嗰個情況咧，個疫情又好，或者係嗰個機場嘅使用率，佢哋會都會因應嗰個情況，會一路考慮嗰個最新情況，而去再做一啲即係誒誒研究嘅。啊，多謝主席。好，跟住阿葉劉淑儀議員。
係收到即係二零三零同埋誒到三一嘅財政年度，即係睇嗰個還款期係點樣啦。咁誒即係暫時嚟講咧，就即係嗰個無論喺個機場建設費嘅費用或者係嗰個即係還款嘅時間，我哋都係用翻即係原本個預算，睇落係有機會做得到。咁但係就我哋會再因應嘅情況，會再去考。
主席，誒，我都係想問翻誒海沙嘅問題啫。其實話海沙、河沙短缺咧，已經係幾年前已經出現㗎啦，嚇。噉就已經係有承辦商咧，即係走遠啲，唔係淨係珠三角，去到馬來西亞嗰啲去揾沙。但我收。
到啲承辦商話咧，佢賣沙都好睏困難，佢運到嚟除咗話運費係打入成本咧，因為你哋醫管局三跑嗰個contractor咧嘅承建商咧，要求嗰啲沙要符合好多環保標準喎，係咪咧？即係要冇冇金屬啊、重金屬啊。
Yes, thank you. Yes, you're correct. As we reported previously to this panel, there was when we started the works, there was a difficulty in obtaining sufficient sand sources from the PRD, and so we looked. Our contractor, working with our contractor, we looked to a much wider scale, to both Malaysia, Philippines.
And within the mainland, a vast majority of the sand we've had is come from customised manufactured sand from Guangdong and and also Fujian. We've also had fill materials from other sources. We've got sand coming from Guangdong as well, marine sand. We've also had marine sand from Guangxi.
咁咧。
誒幾耐啊！
啊。
好啦，而家問題出現啦。而家問題咧就係話，你嘅供應商畀唔到米你，導致到咧你煮唔到飯。
沿海啦，好啦，我一直個問題就係話，我夠知頭先所講嘅食麪係好啦，係快啦，又好食啦，啲學生又中意啦，但係貴啊嘛。
咁而家個問題就係因為你增加咗個比例，而導致到你額外嘅支出呢一部分，究竟有冇問呢個供應商嚟到追討呢方面嘅損失？唔該，主席好啊，邊位回應？
噉啊，呢個呢個要求係咪數來都有有咗幾耐咧？咁如果嗰啲誒承辦商唔係咁清楚，佢運咗嚟，佢應該點處理先，令到佢運翻嚟啲沙係符合你哋要求？
跟住提問，好啲。
一半咧就食飯，一半咧就食麪。但個問題係咧，飯咧就平過一碗麪嘅煮一個飯咧，亦都長啲時間啊。煮麪咧係可能係誒五分鐘，煮一個飯咧係要二十分鐘。
比例噉，其實呢個目的咧就希望啲填料誒放咗落海之後咧，就唔好誒有個好大嘅擴散，咁變咗影響到個海洋生態，咁變咗呢個標準。當然啦，海沙一般嚟講咧，亦都係唔可以係啲污染嘅物料，咁呢個亦都係一另外一個要求嚟嘅。
主席幾耐啊？誒三分鐘啊，唔夠三分鐘。唔該，主席嗱，我用一個好簡單嘅比喻啊。點解我咁著重？究竟你啲海沙點解唔係要問翻contractor嚟到賠翻咧？嗱，個道理噉嘅。假設你而家有一百個同學啊，你而家買晏晝飯畀佢哋食。
We've had also a lot of sand from other areas. We've mentioned Philippines, Malaysia, but also from Taiwan. You're right. We do have to meet exacting standards, and therefore we insist that all our contractors show that the sand they've got is from verifiable sources. It has the appropriate paperwork, and we're very careful in terms of the specification of the sand that will be used.
啊，幾個？O.K.啊，多謝主席，多謝議議員。咁其實咧喺個環境許可證入邊咧都有個要求，就係關於嗰啲誒填料嗰個即係粉，即係最細嗰個即係粉塵嗰個比例。咁其實咧簡單啲講咧，海沙一般嚟講咧就要誒唔可以超過即係誒二十個percent嗰個最細嗰個成分。
The criteria were in the contract originally, so those criteria are very clear. The environmental permit, as Peter mentioned, was set up from the beginning before we commence works. Our specifications are very precise, both from the in terms of meeting the the environmental constraints, also from the engineering constraints as well. And one other source of sand, which just if I could.
Supplement, an important one is we've been using a considerable amount more of public fill than we originally intended. This is from Hong Kong, so again it has a benefit by using the waste materials which still have to meet our specification, our stringent specification. But it is helping remove the vast stockpiles we see in Chun Kwan O and in Tuen Mun, and we've been.
噉你而家咧就增加面嘅比例，所以咧就哦變咗而家我哋要八十碗麪咯，二十碗飯咯。其實你嘅目的就係餵飽啊呢班嘅同學啊嘛。嗱好啦，噉你而家所謂嘅面就係呢個D C M啦，啊就係呢個深層攪拌誒法啦。咁另外咧就係一個嘅誒海沙嚟到嚟到填。
誒多謝主席，我諗誒，我重新翻一樣嘢啦，即係喺嗰個誒。
足夠支付一千四百一十五億嘅，所以係要靠喺出邊誒問誒出邊嘅人去借貸啦。
好啊，唔該你。尤其是你而家嘅借貸成本個息口係有升冇跌嘅，你自己知嘅嚇。好，阿李生。
咧應該係六百九十億，但係隨時會去到七百億㗎啦嚇，唔使講啦。而你純粹銀行借貸啊！
From 18 weeks down to six weeks behind. We've ridden through COVID, and in terms of commercial matters, which I know I have to solve because it's running out of time.
咁所以咧，但係咧，亦都正話誒講咗啦，即係其中嘅誒機場建設費咧，我哋係會收到，當我哋所有借翻嚟嘅錢還曬之後咧，先至會停止收嘅。咁所以正話講咗咧，就會係預計係去到二零三零到三一年度嘅。
表格裏邊咧就講到話係五百五十億到七百八十億嘅，嗰個其實咧係將最低嘅銀碼同埋最高嘅銀碼加埋嘅，即係基本上每一種借貸嘅工具，噉就唔係話我哋要借到去七百八十億，因為裏邊咧都講咧個總值我哋要借嘅咧就係六百九十億港元嘅。
Okay, yes, I'll answer that. I'm afraid I I can't help you with your noodle problem. But can can I put it in terms of the reclamation, which is a very much more complex problem? We established that there were difficulties in obtaining the fill sources from the materials at the early days. This wasn't a desire. This wasn't a
We'll have A instead of B. It was a realisation of the problem we had, and so we worked diligently to overcome that problem to maintain the programme and maintain the budget. I'm very pleased to say, and I'm reporting today, that we are within budget, both within the budget overall budget, but also within the budget of the reclamation. We are getting close to back on programme. We've gone
個問題係噉啊嘛，你係within budget啫，但係你係用多咗錢啊嘛。即係本來你呢餐飯我明明一千蚊賣到單，你話我budget咗一千蚊冇問題，但係本來佢應該八百蚊就賣到單㗎啦。咁而家可能用咗九百蚊啊嘛，噉你個道理唔係同我講話哦，而家九百蚊賣到單都within budget，所以我唔追究。
啊嘛，而係你本身你籤嘅contract呢一個承辦商就應該八百蚊就可以咁多人食飽飯啦，食飽啦咁講啦。咁但係而家因為你畀唔到海沙，即係冇米，導致到你冇辦法之下，你要增加頭先所講面，即係話D C M嘅方法啦嘛。個道理噉樣唔係係咪refin budget呢一個係？
本來唔需要使嘅冤枉錢啊嘛，簡單聽係咁講。唔該，簡單回應啊。In very simple response, there are many benefits in terms of the DCM that are not just in price.係啊，誒，下一位報名嘅議員三分鐘。唔該，主席。誒，我問題係好簡單嘅，可能亦都有少少重。
福嚇誒就係誒一正話啊！陳振英議員咧就問咗我，本來都想問嘅問題，但係嗰個答案係誒不能接受嘅咧。仍然嗱，有關你嘅融資誒嘅嘅計劃咧，就總共去到二零二五年嘅誒總額。
本來就話二百億嘅，你而家話可以去到三百億，正話你哋都誒自己承認，我哋嘅銀行誒借貸嘅銀碼咧係比較大，真係驚喎，真係點解要誒一定個借貸嘅比例係咁重咧？係誒接近一半。
location.
文件畀立法會各位啦，拜拜。
好，係咪李生回答定係邊位回答？
嗰個挖嘅位置喺邊度咧？啊，我請誒機管局作答啊！
Oscar Stretch Mitchell即係即係點樣？即係咩啊？主席可唔可以請機關其他同事解釋下？
好邊位邊位可以答到呢個問題？即係台灣引入嘅。
袁波咧提到喺台灣引入嘅田鳥係咩嚟嘅？
啊，豬處裡嘅誒資料嘅，咁誒亦都咧就係話誒佢哋係有合法嘅，即係我哋睇過啲文件啦，即係應該咁解，機管局就睇過啲。咩叫做唔係係講乜台灣喎？而家講緊係係啊咩process material，即係咩啊？
Hey, as as my colleague has just pointed out, these are dredged materials that are obtained from maintenance dredging, often or other other works. They are then taken ashore and washed and processed to reduce the take out the unsuitable materials, etc. Which part of Taiwan are we talking?
咁滯咧，而誒你成日都話而家現金流就好充裕，暫時咧就未驚過咁上下意思啦嚇。我就想問啦，你可唔可以起碼保證到去到二零二五年咧，基本局係唔會負債去到個程度啊？要公帑嚟填補嘅？
咁另外一方面咧，誒，關於話借貸點解要咁高？噉我諗喺之前嗰個財務報告咧已經講過啦，誒，因為去到個工程完結嘅時候，誒二四二五年嘅時候咧，基本上咧我哋係誒基本局咧靠我哋本身嘅營業同埋個機場建設費嘅收取咧係唔
就唔係去到二零二四年咧，就停止㗎啦。咁誒，關於話銀行嗰度借貸會唔會太多？噉我諗誒喺六百九十億裏邊咧，我哋講緊嘅銀行貸款咧係講緊佔二百至到三百億啦。喺呢個圖裏邊講咗。咁誒，其實咧就正話我都有提到咧，就係我哋就主要咧係因為個。
你睇咧，要平均啲喺用唔同嘅工具，亦都有唔同嘅年期，咁所以咧就會有誒產生呢一個方案嘅啊。噉啊，謝主席好，最後或者朱愛迪語係誒唔該，主席我都係一啲簡單短問短答嘅啫。翻返頭先誒，關於海沙嘅問題咧，我想問誒文件第六段。
係嗰個，嗰係啊，鄭生啊，其實就我喺同機管局一路有了解嘅，咁其實嗰個佢哋係有一個誒疏浚嘅工程，一啲叫做即係geological material，噉就係亦都誒機管局係由同嗰個承建商跟進，就係嗰個疏浚嘅誒合約啊。
即係佢一啲佢一啲誒疏浚嘅誒工程產生嘅物料，即係你倒啲嘢落佢度，就唔係拎啲嘢嚟。唔係疏浚咧，即係話挖掘。你挖啲乜嘢出嚟啊？挖沙咯，咪即係係咪挖海沙？嗱，佢個情況咧就係話係咪喺台灣嘅海域裏面挖海沙？唔係佢係挖一啲咧，佢需要挖嘅東。
東西噉，譬如話，即係一啲需要畫嘅東西，嗰啲係咩嚟㗎？嗱咁誒，佢哋承建商咧就係誒畀個一啲資料畀機機管局嗰啲咧，就係一啲即係需要經過處理咗之後先至係沙嘅物料嚟嘅。咁即係話其實誒，視乎你譬如話，即係如果你響一條河流。
你要去挖一個航道，噉佢可能都有啲河沙。咁但係佢嗰個工程咧，佢最主要就係話佢唔係即係誒，基金覺得嘅資料咧就係話佢唔係採沙，而係因為挖掘而需要挖掘一啲物料。嗰啲物料咧，裏邊有一啲誒物料咧，即係可以重用。即係譬如話，譬如話，如果我
同時。
會議廳。
噉啊！
誒。
個文件。
咁誒。
王志早旅遊專員。
誒邀請佢入嚟。
我會有啊，邱騰華局長。
咁有邀請迪士尼樂園嘅。
當局同埋迪士尼嘅主要嘅負責人。
如果大家準備好，我哋請阿邱局長簡介下。
蔡敏儀副專員同埋楊善利迪士尼嘅行政總監，同埋迪士尼其他嘅相關嘅。
緊守即係睇住個情況，最終唔好返嚟同立法會攞錢。OK，好多謝大家。
噉啊，政府當局同埋香港迪士尼度假區就會有呢個電腦投影片向會委員彙報樂園區二零一九年最財政嘅年度營運嘅情況。
咁跟住下一個議題就係香港迪士尼樂園度假區最新嘅進展嘅報告。噉啊，大家又可以，如果有問題啊，先撳掣。我暫時預計又係四分鐘先啦。
地響誒西九龍裏邊有一個地基工程，或者有一個basement，即係地庫。佢裏邊需要挖掘，但係挖出嚟嗰啲係沙嚟嘅，因為以前西九龍係用沙填嘅。咁所以嗰啲沙係咪可以重用咯？咁所以其實咧就係話佢係我唔知你聽唔聽得聽唔聽得明佢講乜。咁但係我想請教你。
誒。
Thank you.
多謝主席，多謝各位委員先。誒。
Can you make a report on the latest situation?
update on the resort， which I'm sure all of you are interested in.
not only that, but our attendance also grew by five percent and hotel occupancy increased during this period by eight percentage points.
今日呢一個議題咧，原本應該係三月嚟嘅，就係討論即係誒迪士尼樂園喺一八一九年嗰個財政年度嗰個狀況嘅。但係大家都明白啦，即係誒。
香港迪士尼樂園 had a solid first nine months in fiscal 19. During that period, our revenue increased 11% year-on-year, while our net profit increased fourfold. Most importantly, EBITDA, a key measurement of the resort's business fundamentals and prospects, was up by 20%.
Areas around Taiwan, they're doing maintenance dredging from from north, south, east, west. Which direction are we talking about? They come from a variety of areas. Oh, can we can we have more details from AA about that? Come, can we have that, chairman?我我我噉，機管局稍後再補充多啲。
噉啊，因為時間限制，所以而家呢個議程要完啦。不過我知道大家最關心就係嗰個財政嘅問題，同埋嗰個時間會唔會延遲？尤其是大家好擔心咧，到時如果搞唔掂嗰陣時，翻嚟立法會呢度問立法會公堂攞錢。噉啊，我希望基金局即係嗰個財政上去。
一八一九年嗰個情況同今日或者我哋再去即係誒展望出年嘅時候咧，情況係真係自然不同。因為誒一陣可能誒樂園方面嘅誒管理層會同大家交代翻嗰個具體情況啦。但係一八一九年咧，佢個財政年度係由九月至九月咧，頭嗰三。
三季咧係一個即係比較好嘅發展。我哋見到近年嚟，我哋隨住即係話誒新嘅旅遊藍圖啊，同埋誒樂園方面做嘅工作咧，我哋見到有九個月係比較向好嘅發展，即係無論喺入場人數嘅收入方面。但係一八一九嗰個財政年度嘅最後一季。
係咧，就正正亦都係我哋舊年即係誒年中開始，即係由六月至九月嗰個誒社會嘅事件誒，令到即係誒不單止係誒遊客嘅人數，以致香港嘅市民喺即係出外嘅時候都有影響。咁所以我哋見到即係嗰個逆轉係相當之急而。
如果我哋即係再去展望，即係誒喺今年即係一九二零年呢個財政年度咧，更加係雪上加霜。噉啊，大家記得啦，舊年年底嘅誒第四季咧，嗰個旅遊數字係簡單嚟講係減咗一半。今年嘅第一季係減咗百分之八十。如果我哋睇第二季咧，係百分減咗百分之九十九點九添。咁所以係。
係一個噉嘅處境之下，我哋去睇翻、回顧翻一八一九年嗰個樂園嘅情況。誒，但係誒喺誒咁多種情況之下咧，誒我哋仍然覺得即係嗰個誒作為一個誒旅遊嘅基建咧，誒迪士尼樂園確實係香港即係誒對我哋個經濟係有一個正面嘅幫。
因為我哋每年睇得到，以舊年為例，以一八九零為例咧，佢經濟收益都有八十八億元嘅經濟收益，亦都有一百三十誒一百五十七億嘅誒額外嘅消費，亦都僱用咗五千幾個誒即全職人員、二千幾個兼職人員等等。咁所以呢個誒我哋覺得誒係重要嘅，而且喺我。
銀和金選項。
And of course, we will continue the momentum of this program as the local market will be our key focus during the initial part of reopening period.
作為結果，The Resorts第四季的表現受影響，尤其是在夏季期間，這是一個高峯旅遊季節，特別是對於家庭訪客。
我們也繼續強化在本地香港市場的定位。 for the full year, 41% of our guest mix was from Hong Kong.
我們 grateful for the unwavering support of our Magic Access guests, and in return, we are very excited to welcome them back with more special offers and programmes.
第二列顯示實際財政年度，你可見結果受影響，由減少過夜遊客在第四季。
Our performance can be attributed to our unique Disney storytelling, one-of-a-kind attractions and experiences, and special events that bring to life our beloved characters.
And finally, per capita spending at the theme park increased by 4%, which represents the 10th consecutive year of growth, and full year occupancy was 74%, only slightly below the prior year due to fourth quarter impacts.
However, in the fourth quarter of fiscal 19, which is July through September for our fiscal year, Hong Kong's overall tourism industry was severely impacted as overnight vacation arrivals dropped 35% in that particular period.
在 addition to having a number of comprehensive strategies in place and a multi-year planning approach, the team has remained flexible, agile and very prudent when it comes to managing the resort through the recent events.
The full-year attendance was 6.5 million. Our continued focus on diversifying our market reach led to encouraging double-digit growth from a number of overseas markets, such as Japan, Thailand and South Korea.
如果你 look at this chart at the 12-month results ending June 2019， you can see we enjoyed an encouraging year-on-year growth in revenue and EBITDA， and delivered a positive net income。
Our key business strategies will continue to yield results. Our nimble marketing and sales efforts are tailored for many unique markets. For example, with the launch of Ant-Man and the Wasp Nano Battle, we reached out to trade partners and consumers covering over 30 major cities in the region.
Our performance these few years shows the strong fundamentals of our business. Our full year revenue for fiscal 19 stood at six billion, and full year EBITDA was 1.1 billion, with 10 consecutive years of positive results. Fiscal 19 net loss increased slightly to 105 million.
key attributes to the strong performance included different member-exclusive programmes with special offerings. A great example was leveraging the summer movie release of Toy Story 4, the Oscar winner for best animated feature film, which created an exclusive event which was extremely well received by our loyal fans.
嚟嗰個疫情受控嘅同時咧，我哋都即係誒及早同園方去討論喺作好誒所有防疫準備嘅時候咧，誒喺上個禮拜佢能夠重開，我哋都見到好多人好開心，即係誒繼續去享用呢個樂園。咁呢個時候，我交翻畀誒樂園嘅管理層去講講誒個文件，唔該。好啊，噉我請阿Stephanie。
during the initial reopening.
作為公園開，健康和安全，的我們的客和客人是我們的首要優先。
and the most exciting development is the castle of magical dreams in its final stage of transformation.
The park reopened with a number of promotional offers for local guests to enjoy both our hotels and our park experiences.
enhanced social distancing and hygiene measures and compliance with the government and health authorities are implemented across all of our experiences.
我們也已延長了Magic Access成員資格的有效期，並將推出一係列的獨家活動及慶典，來歡迎他們重返公園。
Starting from this summer, seasonal events, new offerings and a milestone celebration will be rolling out to provide many reasons for guests to visit and return.
一數 of 興起的 offerings are in the pipeline, featuring some of the latest and most popular characters and stories from Disney, Pixar and Marvel to welcome all of our guests back.
Of course, like many businesses in the community, we have been making every possible effort to weather the storm. The most encouraging and exciting news is the reopening of the park just a few days ago.
作為政府繼續審視入境遊客安排，我們亦將迅速調整我們的市場及銷售策略，以誘引非本地遊客，特別是那些市場在近距離。
我們將繼續借鑑迪士尼強大的國際吸引力，來建立一個堅實的粉絲羣。我們舉辦了多項針對性活動，並提供獨家優惠，作為新設施的預覽。
especially with the government quarantine requirements for inbound visitors, we are focusing on welcoming local guests. Hong Kong Disneyland Resort is among the top of mind getaway destinations of Hong Kong people.
And as reported by the Walt Disney Company in recent earning calls, the significant decrease in visitation to Hong Kong, together with the coronavirus outbreak, will negatively impact our fiscal 20 business results.
我們繼續利用科技驅動業務。一個例子是成功實現130%的銷售增長，於 Singles Day、Double Eleven 期間，透過電商渠道在中國。
This year, we have all been facing an unprecedented challenging time that extended from the last quarter of fiscal nineteen and continued through the pandemic. When we joined the community's measures to contain the virus with an almost five-month park closure.
We are building off our strong Disney movies and stories. Our second Marvel themed attraction has quickly grown to become the most popular attraction at the park, and continues with a higher mix of young adults and male guests, as well as driving attendance growth from the Philippines, Thailand and Korea.
Mr. Chairman, thank you, Secretary Yau. We were originally scheduled to report our fiscal 19 results to this panel in March, but obviously schedules were impacted by the pandemic and a lot has happened in the last few months. So I'm going to quickly go through Hong Kong Disneyland's fiscal 19 performance and give a more recent.
On our annual pass program, which is called the Magic Access Program, it was one of our strongest drivers in fiscal nineteen, with a record of eight visits per member throughout the year. This resulted in record attendance and total spending from the Magic Access Program. We also saw the trend of local guests purchasing higher tiers of this program through the.
to welcoming guests back to our resort.
plans are underway to offer a special welcome to health workers to the park.
We're also partnering with FoodLink Foundation, our regular community food donation program.
This community contribution will continue to be extended throughout the year through our NGO partnerships.
When the park reopened, we invited underprivileged families in the neighbourhood to celebrate with us.
alot of work has gone on to make sure we're all taking the necessary steps to keep our guest and cast members safe, healthy and happy.
作為即時 relief to our travel trade partners， complimentary parking at the resort's coach park was offered to them.
to donate close to 8.5 tons of surplus food since February, helping to make over 20,000 meals for underprivileged families.
Almost 270,000 jobs have been created throughout the years, both directly at the resort and indirectly within our extended Hong Kong community.
The positive impact of Hong Kong Disneyland also extends beyond the resort. The resort has brought over 100 billion of added economic value since the park's opening.
While we spare no effort to recover business, we never stop the support for the community, especially during a time when bringing positive energy means a lot more than usual.
undoubtedly, we have all been in uncharted territory this past year, and we've had to constantly adapt so we can approach each situation in the best way possible.
This major project of our expansion plan is expected to open later this year, together with an all-new nighttime spectacular show to celebrate the resort's 15th anniversary.
作為迪士尼的執行主席鮑勃·艾格説：，這些是挑戰性的時刻，但迪士尼已經多次證明我們是無可置疑的韌性。我們的未來一直都很光明，而且仍然如此。
我們捐贈6,000迪士尼物品到 Princess Margaret Hospital 通過「Thank You Health Heroes」 Initiative，作為對醫療工作者的感謝，他們一直在前線照顧病人，24小時。
for the more than five thousand workforce at the resort, I cannot thank them enough for working together to respond to the many difficulties, from making countless adjustments to working schedules, implementing extra hygiene precautions in the resort.
嘅瘋狂fans啦，專業級啦。
係，啊，誒，等等。
Thank you, Chairman, for your time. Thank you, Stephanie.
This is true for Hong Kong Disneyland as well.
我們正在創造獨一無二的迪士尼體驗，來 delight 我們的客人。
feel fortunate with our position. Our cast are very important to delivering our experiences.
Our business has a strong foundation, and we're positioned well for the future.
With the launch of the Castle of Magical Dreams and Hong Kong Disneyland's 15th anniversary later this year.
香港迪士尼樂園是 committed to play a pivotal role in supporting the local community and ensuring the resort remains a top tourist destination in Asia.
We are confident that the park's reopening will benefit Hong Kong's tourism industry, and we will continue to work closely as our business partners to attract visitors back to Hong Kong.
噉我而家就開放畀委員發問。第一位係譚文浩議員，跟住係梁繼昌議員。誒唔該主席。誒我想咧，即係喺過去呢個疫情啦，大家都面對緊。咁誒迪士尼，我想確認一點咧，就係冇進行過裁員，亦都係冇計劃裁員嘅，係咪啊？唔該主席。
Yes, we have been very fortunate with our financial stability that we have been able to manage the situation quite well, and we have not had to lay off any of our employees at the resort. And we're again navigating through this storm that everyone has gone through, but we we.
係，好唔該。誒，另外一個問題咧，就係即係喺過去喺呢個疫情等等咧，都係可以做到即係不裁員嘅情況咧。噉我都覺得係誒，即係好remarkable，係可以做得到呢一件事。噉我就有啲意見嘅啫，純粹係嗱，譬如你而家係諗緊即係點？
噉樣做好啲啦。噉你都睇到咧，其中一個令到你哋破紀錄嘅地方咧，就係呢個奇妙處處通嗰個嘅業績。噉我想問啊，你哋咧啊，我先申報一下啦，我都係奇妙處處通嘅嘅嘅一個member嚟嘅。噉我我我想我想問一樣嘢咧，就係誒，你哋有冇諗有冇做咧？應該咁講啦，就係有啲嘅。
focus group就係揾翻呢啲嘅誒年費嘅會員，就去問下佢意見，即係園區裏邊有啲咩要改善啊。無論係服務啊、飲食啊、餐飲啊，或者係各樣嘢有冇咧？如果有嘅，如果冇嘅話咧，我建議你哋做呢樣嘢就可能係誒抽出嚟，即係唔好話。
定叫人舉手，因為舉手嗰啲咧就未必真係畀到一啲好真嘅意見你，同埋好多太好主觀。可能你係考慮抽，可能咧我建議你做法咧都分黐啊，即係一班咧就可能係喂，起碼至少個個月都入嚟一次嘅，甚至乎係即係一年可以入誒雙位數字嘅人次。咁呢啲即係一啲所有。
which features Dumbo here and and and its called business recovery plan in the pipeline.
好，thank you。噉啊，梁繼昌議員。
Now my third question relates to the slide.
your revenue base. I I do think we need a few percentage increase in in gas coming from other countries. That that is my view and my second question.
點解咁得意咧？你嘥咁多錢，即係我如果冇做嘅話，如果有你可以分享一下啦。你你講有冇做？如果冇嘅話咧，我強力建議你哋做下呢一樣嘢。唔該。好啊。
Can you tell this panel what are the directions of the business recovery plan? What do you want to achieve?
咁呢度咧就係一組人喺裏邊咧，就可能係抽誒十個嚟，有咗個focus group嚟，有睇睇佢哋嘅睇法。一啲咧可能咧就係買咗年票，但係可能係誒我一年可能係誒十次左右嘅啊啊，或者少於十次。噉你睇一睇嗰啲噉，跟住另外group咧就係可能買咗，但係咦原來一年先嚟得一兩。
Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Yes, our Magic Access members are considered our most loyal fans, so thank you for your membership. We've had quite a lot of success actually in getting and collecting feedback, and we've adjusted our program year to year based on that feedback. In fact,
even most recently this past week, as we offered our Magic Access a day in advance early registration because we are requiring reservations to the park. We want to manage the capacity for the park, so they get that first chance. And so we've been collecting feedback through various channels. We collect it not only through our survey process, but we also
所以收集透過guest relations， as well as our call centre。所以，all of this information is collected。In fact, I'm looking at it daily because we want to make sure we're responding quite quickly. We'll send out communication to our Magic Access members through electronic emails just to make sure that they have all the information that they need. So just a time only to just drum in for that.
for for those member, I think this an important part is it's not just doing a survey. Because doing a survey, I mean, I just only take you know three or four minutes. I just give you tick tick tick, and are you going to ask me an extra comment? And you ask me to type, I probably not doing it. But what I'm recommended is actually is more in depth in depth.
consultation with a focus group, group of people. You talk, I'm only talking about maybe ten. You just randomly pick them, right? Just ten of them from each group. As I mentioned, you know, those are, you know, super fans and some of them, you know, why you didn't come to the park? Why you bought the the park office? There's some some issue with that. So that that
What I mean, I know you, I understand that you know by your your guest centre and all that you you took you know some of the feedback, but what I'm looking for is more in depth, maybe just you know one hour something like that, you know to have a discussion group with them. That's that's my recommendation. That's all. Thank you, thank you, Chairman, for the suggestion. And we are conducting focus groups on a period.
我講真，我有about three three questions only. The number one is the second slide concerning the full year result offset by the quarter four impact. Just one thing, I I need to confirm with the company on the revenue row.
Does it mean that even taken into account of the fourth quarter impact, you have no impact on the revenue at all? Because I I can see that that the percentage is just nil. Just just a very simple question. And my second question relates to slide number three, which sets out the the composition of the gas mix.
Do you think that the composition mix here is ideal? Now, Hong Kong residents comprise about forty-one percent, but I do have a feel that we should attract more guests from other countries. Now, only twenty-six percent of those guests comes from other country, but in order to diversify.
啊啊唔該，主席啊，多謝局長同埋啊。
啊，楊善妮小姐咧，即係今日咁尊重，即係出席我哋嘅會議啦。就嗯，我第一個問題咧，我想問問咧，又聽聽到啊。
able to cope with cash payment, especially the cash payment to your cars and all your employees. Thank you. Stepheny, thank you. Three questions.
出 of this recovery situation quickly, and the management has worked very hard to make sure that our costs are managed tightly as we get out of this recovery situation. Okay, thank you。跟住少咖啡魚。
Are very valid and offerings have have really supported them, and I'm proud that our team has also put in place what we call ambassadors, so Japanese-speaking cast members as well that are able to support that market.
Although I I don't think you have the detail yet, but what are the assumptions underlining the business recovery plan? And I'm also quite concerned that what about your cash flow, current cash flow as at today? You
Yes. Four questions. Four. Okay. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. That is correct on the revenue. That means it was flat year over year, so no decline or increase. Regarding guest mix, yes, absolutely. We believe that we should put all of our efforts toward every possible market, and we agree.
That the other markets such as Thailand, Taiwan, all of them have the opportunity. Philippines, all of them have various opportunities. In fact, we were even thrilled to see Japan increase forty percent last year in fiscal nineteen, and we are pressing on all of these opportunities.
All of them have different holidays and different patterns, and so we partner quite closely with the individual trade partners in each of these markets as well to make sure that we are in fact. Chairman, can I just put in one more question? How do we differentiate our the attraction here in Hong Kong with the Tokyo Disneyland? Because I I do think if you want to attract
People from Japan, you have to have a different product. Absolutely, yes. We take quite great pride in the fan base that we have and what's grown more than double digit year over year for the past three years from Japan. In fact, they are big fans of the Duffy family and so they've been visiting quite.
頻繁地，去 enjoy our character experiences， and in fact they don't have the long queues that that they would experience in Tokyo. And quite frankly, our expense for travelling here and enjoying a vacation at Hong Kong Disneyland is more reasonable. And so there's many reasons why.
Chairman, could you ask Stephanie to answer my last question about the recovery plan, please? Yes, Mr. Chairman, we have actually thought very hard about this recovery plan. We're, as I mentioned, in unprecedented times with no arrivals into Hong Kong, and so our initial focus, as I mentioned, will be very much on our local audiences.
我們 feel that the local audiences are ready to get out of their homes to enjoy a nice staycation at our resort, stay one or two nights in the hotels and enjoy the park experience. So our immediate focus is going to be not only on continuing to attract the Magic Access members, but also to make sure that our local audience.
have the opportunity to have a nice vacation. But then, following that, we're going to pay very close attention to other close vicinity markets and the travel bubbles that the government is working diligently on, and we'll jump on those opportunities as well to make sure that we can pursue that. And of course, our expansion plan is what we really believe can be leveraged.
To entice all of these markets to come back to Hong Kong and enjoy the great experiences that Disney has to offer. No, not also any any cash flow issue now. Just just quickly one one word yes or no. We're in a very comfortable position of obviously this impact of being closed for five months had a big significant impact on the business.
但我們有通過我們的正向IBA，如我所説，10個連續年份，和，所以我們處於一個幸運的狀況，我們可以繼續保持我們的演員，保留才華，和繼續評估情況。我們也會繼續管理我們的成本，非常謹慎。我們知道我們不會得到。
係。
Stephanie。
係阿邱局長啊，啊，我畀誒元芳先答。
嗰度咧，嗰個利息税項啊，同埋折舊嗰度咧，你減少咗。嗱，如果喺噉嘅情況持續住，即係要蝕錢。
而嗰個遊客其實又即係睇唔到，又好快會加上去上邊。咁即係雖然你集中做本地市民啫，咁但係其實即係你如果你唔減低嘅成本嘅話，我都係好驚，即係將來都係搞唔掂啊，主席。
啊，其中有委員就講過，即係你哋冇裁員啦，即係過去嘅時間噉樣。咁其實我知道樂園其實冇開過嘅。咁其實如果即係冇裁員嘅話，咁其實過去冇開嘅話，噉佢哋啲人工啊，冇又冇啲啊，即係調整過啊等等嘅情況咧。
情開花嘅話咧，我相信都要一定嘅時間去recover啦噉樣。噉我見到頭先啊，總裁都即係啊，總裁都講咗，即係佢哋希望集中翻喺本地嘅市民嗰個嘅消費啦。咁呢個方向其實都係好嘅。咁嗱，我想講講咧，即係嗱喺第第啊文件上面第七版嗰度咧，就講緊即係喺啊。
We we have had to take some measures. As I've mentioned, we've prudently managed our cost. One of the measures that we did take is asking all of our vice president executive level positions to take a twenty to thirty percent pay cut. Which we appreciate their commitment in doing so. We also have asked our employees to.
要取一個一天 unpaid 綜假，which 實際上 stop 了上個星期，所以他們做咗兩個月。我們開始咗呢個過程喺四月，而我們 stop 咗。喺公佈開幕嘅時候，我們需要所有嘅演員返嚟支援呢個體驗。所以我們感謝所有嘅演員，所有嘅員工所作出嘅承諾。
好，唔該。啊，即係歡迎佢哋，即係喺嗰個時間同埋啲同志一齊共度時間啊！就誒，而唔裁員嘅話，都即係多謝你哋啦，即係可以幫佢補住我哋嗰啲嘅就業啦。嗱，啊主席，即係局長，其實老老實實，即係正常嚟講咧，即係佢哋迪士尼咁大，佢哋營運一個樂園，其實我我哋其實我就唔好想參與人哋。
即係公司點樣營運？不過你話經過海洋公園嘅事件嘅話，咁即係我哋做議員，我哋點樣唔參與咧？尤其是迪士尼樂園，其實我哋有即係咁多股份，即係我哋好擔心。即係如果經營得即係嘅經歷講畀我聽唔好嘅話咧，到時候就重蹈覆轍。所以即係點解今日要嘥少少時間去問咧？
即係尤其是睇佢啲數，其實過去開咁多次會，我其實主席我都冇睇嘅。佢啲數係算啦，佢哋應該佢哋搞掂啦，係咪？咁但係其實而家真係唔可以唔睇嘅。嗱，喺你報告講畀我哋聽咧，其實三分一其實就係國內嘅遊客嚟嘅。咁而家即係喺社會事件上面，你見到其實個遊客其實有減少。咁嚟緊話就算疫，
二零一八年同埋二零一九年啦，即係你嗰個收入啦，係咪？嗱，你二零一八年嗰個收入咧，大概六十億啦，去到二零一九年咧個收入去到都係六十億，就六十億六十億四千萬，噉啊，二零一八年就六十億二千萬噉樣啦，係咪？嗱，你個個收入其實差唔多，但係你嘅營運成本咧，你見到你二零一八年嘅時咧就四。
十六億六，你二零一九年咧就上升咗，就去到四十九億二嘅，即係嗰個收入其實就唔係多咗好多。但係你嘅支出嘅話咧，其實你係大咗嘅。而同樣地咧，即係你要扣除嗰個嘢，其實每一年你都要有還利息啊、還款項啊、又折舊啊等等嗰啲嘢啦。二零一八年咧就十三億五啦，二零一九年咧就。
十一億二噉，你嘅折舊咧，你已經再折舊少咗啦。你計少條數啦，我唔知點解你咁叻，即係點樣計少條數啦。總之，如果唔係你計翻二零一八年嘅時候咧，即係如果你嘅折舊率係一樣嘅話咧，其實你喺二零一九年你蝕嘅數咧就唔係一億零五千萬，你應該係蝕緊二億幾啦。已經O K，你只不過喺嗰個撥數嗰。
我請完。哦，請阿Stephanie，Yes。
Four questions。我請，好啊，阿邱局長。
噉我估計係真係好似你文件所講，係充滿挑戰嘅一年。
第二個問題就係隨住，即係今年嘅情況並不理想。
我第一個問題想問咧，就係誒喺一七年咧撥咗一百零九億畀迪士尼，作為興建五個項目。
誒，今年一月底開始迪士尼開始關完啦，去到六十八先重開。噉佢嘅整個收入資金流一定造成好大影響。
誒一八年迪士尼嘅數據咧，睇嚟係誒相對係好嘅，但係一九年嘅情況咧，誒面對社會事件啦，跟住落去就係疫情。
咁做事嘅話咧，我哋都會即係只要喺合理同埋我哋有能力嘅情況之下，我哋都會全力去支持嘅。迪士尼公園就一樣，希望你繼續努力啦。多謝。誒，跟住阿姚思榮議員。誒，多謝主席。
第三個問題就係而家香港誒迪士尼面臨噉嘅困境，佢總部有乜嘢措施係支援香港迪士尼？包括譬如會唔會減收佢嘅管理費或者專利費？
咁會唔會因為噉樣樣而影響到誒誒資金流應有冇問題？因為你有筆錢喺度，但會唔會影響到嗰五個項目嘅興建，或者你會調整對呢五個項目興建嗰個有關嘅安排咧？噉樣？
政府會唔會會誒預計到迪士尼喺未來會唔會出現好似海洋公園嘅情況，即係話誒資金流斷裂，去到咩情況先要出現呢個？有冇預計到咩情況會出現資金斷裂嘅可能咧？噉樣？
第四個問題就係迪士尼最近推出誒佢哋已經誒重開園區啦，但係海洋公園我睇到係好多嘅優惠畀市民嘅，或者畀業界誒下一階段迪士尼會唔會有一啲嘅措施優惠香港市民或者業界咧噉樣？
Yes, definitely agree that we're in for a recovery ahead of us. So we have to be very prudent, as I mentioned, in managing our cost. We were quite surprised by the dramatic impact of arrivals in the fourth quarter of the last fiscal year, fiscal 19, but immediately we started to take action.
and we reduced our expenses quite quickly. One example of that is we have natural attrition. So instead of filling positions very quickly, we we decided to protect the positions that we already had and allow that natural attrition to happen. So that actually started many months before the pandemic situation.
situation that we had. In addition to that, of course, we looked at all of our marketing and sales expenses. As an example, we renegotiated contracts for support and services that we receive at the resort, and many of our vendors were willing to make substantial reductions. There's inflationary cost, of course, that that will impact us.
講多一句，主席，好喺喺，就算喺而家呢一刻都好啦，即係我哋對於喺外國嘅任何企業過嚟香港。
Thank you.
噉啊，下一位陸續同意。
個收支咧係有好轉嘅。
甚至咧，如果冇誒盈利或者冇收入嘅時候咧，佢會收唔到。
Catch, catch, trouble problems。我我補充。好啊，阿局長。阿姚先元問嘅問題裡面咧，就係。
恢復嘅時候咧，我哋大家都要即係誒注意，即係嗰個營運情況，尤其是喺嗰個開支嘅管理方面。咁呢方面嚟講咧，我哋同誒公司係一路都密切去聯絡。同埋會唔會減嗰個管理費啊？同埋嗰個。
certainly for the last year, but we believe that we have been very prudent in allowing us to make the appropriate adjustments to our cost and our infrastructure and being able to continue the success of the business in the spirit of the expansion plans.
所以我們再評估一下，什麼意思？對一些其他建設努力正在進行，但現在擴張當然已經進行得很順利，我們認為這是我們能夠恢復和幫助香港社區驅動到來的重要因素。
the the progress for our expansion, as you can see from the castle and and our guests, we're very excited to see the progress that was made. We started our expansion, as this panel knows, with the Moana show, which led to Ant-Man and the Wasp launch in fiscal nineteen, and then in a few months' time we will unveil the.
final product of our castle, along with the nighttime show that I mentioned. So our efforts around the expansion continued. Quite pleased that the construction teams could make progress even during the pandemic situation. However, there was a slowdown of getting construction materials and other things that we're still assessing. So
你 also asked about just our expectation in the long run in the situation. Our competing park is actually a very different business model, very different financial structure, and very different stage of development. So the comparisons for us are not as meaningful, but we do understand.
That we need to be very prudent in managing our cost and our cash flow, and that has been certainly something that the management has been very very focused on. And I look at this information every day. Of course, we have our board that also reviews that information as well. So it's it's been a tough road.
頭先有另外議員都問過，就係話喺而家呢一個噉嘅即係經濟大環境之下，點樣確保即係誒呢類嘅主題公園經營咧？我諗有兩部分嘅。第一咧就係話喺個經營上邊咧，大家睇得到咧，就係舊年我哋引述咧，就係頭嗰九個月咧，喺正常情況之下咧，其實誒呢個樂園嗰個經營嗰
不過，亦都有部分就係話，好似舊年下半年或者今年年初，甚至要即係誒停開呢一部分係其實冇人能夠預計，亦都冇人能夠準確去點去處理嘅。咁誒短時間嚟講咧，姚議員問到就係話，即係如果係應對嗰個現金流等等咧，我哋同誒公司咧係有一個安排佢。
有個備用信貸嘅咁變咗，佢係嗰個可以正正就係我嚟應付，即係喺現金流嗰方面。但係長遠嚟講咧，我諗即係我都要即係誒預告一聲，就係誒跟住落去嚟緊呢，即係一年或者係多過一年咧，我相信係最艱難嘅時候，因為喺全世界嚟講，各地即係嗰個旅遊未。
誒，主席誒，就住嗰個管理費同埋專營權咧，誒，大家記得以往討論嘅時候咧，呢一個喺誒上一次嘅時候作咗一個調整，佢哋都係同嗰個營誒收入係掛鈎嘅。咁所以咧，其實如果喺而家呢個艱難時候咧，如果冇收入嘅時候咧，誒，相應嚟講咧，誒呢一部分嘅支出係會少咗。
啊！畀我哋知道。
第二點咧，就係講翻嗰個營運嘅問題啦。
咁呢一批嘅遊客，你哋有冇做過啲市場調查？
嗰個嘅印象好差，嗰樣嘢影響嘅。
誒有冇放呢個無薪假嘅情況？呢個第一點，我想了解。
其實就影響就好大啦，七至九月就下跌咗三成嘅遊客。
誒，你哋個客量嗰個減少嘅情況，有冇啲不同嘅預預測？
誒當然係幾好啦，係咪？咁但係黑暴之後，再之後嘅疫情咧。
可能會減少幾多咧？嗱，減有我估計就一定會減㗎啦嚇，除非有奇蹟出現啦嚇，做啲非常好嘅推廣。
誒，我想問下咧，即係樂園有冇評估？誒，就算疫情之後。
誒唔好話，淨係即係有信心啊！我哋有評估啊，噉樣唔該，主席。好啊，唔該，Debbie。
咁減完之後點樣可以填補翻嗰個客量？減完之後會唔會導致係一個長期嘅虧蝕？
咁一八至一九年咧，舊嘅數據咧，其實喺而家呢一刻就參考價值唔大嘅，特別一八一九年咧就係誒六月之前啊，就特別係即係黑暴之前。
多謝主席。誒，第一個問題咧，就係想迪士尼就即係清楚翻，你話冇裁員啦，咁有冇大幅嘅減薪？即係喺呢半年之內，即係完全差唔多係即係閂咗門嘅情況之下。
減幾多就會誒，仲係維持到平衡。減幾多咧，就可能會蝕錢啦。誒，特別係內地遊客，內地遊客咧佔誒三成幾、三分之一嘅即係遊客量。咁呢班遊客咧最受黑暴嗰個不愉快經歷。
當然啦，黑暴咧，唔亦都唔單止係嚇走內地客嘅，其他地方嘅客人咧都會受唔少嘅影響嘅。呢一啲客人又會減少幾多咧？即係話你哋嗰個評估不同情況之下嗰個未來嘅財政，你哋點樣去有個數字？可唔可以披露下？
主席。
個嘅係。
土地即係個第二期嘅係六十公頃嘅土地，呢一個做法。
成個嘅係旅遊業同埋航空業嘅模式咧，都會有個災難性嘅影響嘅。
有個評估，有個預案。我今日知道咧，佢係會希望多啲本地客啦。可唔可以之後有啲數據畀我哋咧？好啊，咁希望誒粵方或者當局可以稍後畀多啲資料我哋咯。跟住胡志偉議員。
Yes, with regard to your first point around any pay cuts or any other leave requires, we did encourage our staff to take their holiday leave, their vacation leave. That's like most companies are doing, is to avoid any impacts to jobs and positions. As I mentioned, we also
asked all of our vice president executives to take a twenty to thirty percent permanent reduction. That's still in place, as a matter of fact, until we feel like we have a firm footing on our situation. And then for our frontline teams, we also asked them to take one day unpaid leave for two months. So those were the measures that we.
felt that we had to take in order to manage and navigate through this situation. The park will continue to focus on recovery and we're going to adjust our plans as much as possible. Obviously, we need to be agile and nimble. We need to watch how we can grab the.
opportunities when we do have inbound visitors, but we are not sitting back and waiting for inbound visitors. We're going to continue to focus on the local market and make sure that we can increase our Magic Access membership. It's a great opportunity. All you have to do is come twice to our park and you've paid for that membership.
So it offers many other exclusive benefits to that membership as well. So we think it's a great opportunity for families who aren't able to travel this summer to enjoy the benefits of that. But even for locals who do not have an interest in the Magic Access program, we're going to provide many more opportunities, local promotions and other offers.
主席，主席，我希望咧，元芳對於即係疫情之後嗰個內地客同埋其他客人嗰度咧。
即係我只係想提一提誒，其實呢個都係阿邱騰華局長喺講海洋公園嘅時間咧，就提咗一啲嘅形勢嘅。第一，佢就提出咗就係話咧，喺區裏邊主題公園嘅競爭係非常之激烈嘅。第二個佢又提咗就係話咧，喺疫情之後咧，而家個誒。
呢啲嘅説法咧，唔係喺呢一份文件見到，但係喺海洋公園申請撥款嘅時候見到。咁第一個，我當然就想搞清楚啦。邱局長就係你呢兩句嘅説話咧，其實係唔係應用喺呢個迪士尼公園身上邊咧，都係同樣有效嘅一個即係形勢嘅研判。咁如果係嘅話，
如果係個話，噉我當然想聽下你講畀我聽。究竟你遇到呢一種嘅係災難性嘅係即係誒結構性嘅係方向改變，同埋區裏邊競爭咁激烈嘅時間，有啲咩策略去處理啦？因為喺海洋公園個case裏邊咧，你係指出就係誒，因為。
有呢一種嘅安排之下，有呢一種嘅形勢嘅話咧，所以海洋公園原先要求嘅係一百零七億嘅撥款，係要有個全新嘅係啲機動遊戲嘅，或者一啲所謂嘅吸引力嘅內容咧，都變成就一個唔審慎嘅方案要改變，甚至要縮小呢一個嘅係海洋公園嘅。
規模以迎合最新嘅形勢發展嘅，咁如果係同樣嘅邏輯係適用嘅話，一亦都想請教下局長你，嗯喺今日背景之下，海洋喺呢個迪士尼公園，佢嚟緊係會有第二期可以再claim嗰。
主題樂園嘅競爭咧係真係全球性嘅，咁誒。
迪士尼樂園佢本身有好多即係佢自己喺樂園以外嘅，譬如喺知識產權上邊啊、電影啊等等。
第二部分嚟講咧，我頭先亦都講過，就係話成個旅遊業咧，全球嚟講咧，會隨住嗰個疫情。
無論係海洋公園，無論係迪士尼，都係當然誒，佢哋誒本身所具備嘅條件係有分別嘅，譬如誒。
等等，嗱呢部分嘅工作咧，我哋而家係同誒迪士尼公司係誒做緊一個商討，所以喺現階段嚟講咧，我暫時可以講到係咁多。唔該，主席。最後一位啊，李慧瓊議員。
政府當局會唔會係重新去審視？因為個形勢有變，唔係咁簡單就畀多啲地理投資更多嘅話咧，就能夠回應到嗰個客觀嘅環境。第二就係有第二期嘅用地開展咗嘅時候，如果真係畀你claim到嘅話，其實都係講緊就話政府嘅資源塔咧將。
將會唔簡單，因為由二零一由一八年到二三年之間，個一百零幾億嘅係新嘅係即係項目發展咧，政府嘅承擔額咧都去咗五十五十噉樣樣嘅處境嘅。咁如果係六十公頃嘅第二期用地嘅進一步發展嘅話，可能嗰個嘅係即係發展成本咧係一個相當巨大嘅數字。
喺噉嘅背景之下，咁政府當局又點樣睇咧？到最後就係因為噉樣樣嘅話，因為土地資源係咁貴佛嘅時候，究竟政府當局係咪仍然或者應該？你有冇同呢個迪士尼再探討過？就係究竟佢有幾大嘅可能性去到二零二五年嘅時間，會因為呢一個嘅係旅客嘅人？
人數上升或者係房價上升，然後就係會claim呢一塊土地，還是去考慮過成個投資嘅形勢，覺得再claim呢一塊土地都係唔合適嘅話，係盡早將呢一塊土地放翻出嚟作其他嘅用途咧。三個問題，多主席誒，局長誒，三個問題第一部分咧就係誒。
誒，但係呢一個競爭係適用於每一個樂園，都要不斷誒進步。咁所以亦都係即係，議員頭先都指出啦，就係喺一六一七年嘅時候咧，呢一個立法會都曾經批核過，畀佢進行即係新一期嗰個發展。咁亦都有因為咁咧，而有部分嘅設施係不斷去落成更新，繼續投資，繼續吸引。係噉，呢個一定。
同埋嗰個復甦嘅過程咧，受到好大嘅衝擊同埋變化。呢個亦都係冇人能夠避免嘅，因為如果你話到今日為止，好多地方係仍然都係有一個旅遊嘅限制嘅時候咧，我哋好難期望即係任何嘅旅客，無論嚟自邊個地方都好啦，翻返去原有嘅局面。咁呢個都要維持一段時間。但係如果我哋睇翻我哋，
喺兩年前推出嘅旅遊藍圖，或者係誒我哋近期即係喺誒同誒旅發局重開嗰啲策略裏面咧，我都著重翻咧就係唔係呢段時間冇旅客就等於唔做誒推廣宣傳，反而就係話喺呢段時間裏面咧，本地人嗰個旅遊經驗咧，將會成為我哋將來成功嘅因素之一。噉我呢？
要唔再重複第三方面嚟講咧，就住嗰個將來嚟講咧，嗱第一期嗰個擴展計劃喺經過立法會撥款咧，誒一路在進行進行當中咧。會員頭先所問嘅咧，可能係喺第二期或者在及後嗰啲土地使用嘅時候咧，我哋係有一個條款嘅，我哋同嗰個誒迪士尼嘅公司咧係有一個。
個誒安排咧，就係話要誒視乎某啲嘅情況會唔會延展第二誒，或者將將來甚至第三期嗰個情況，裏面亦都有啲條款係包括咧。譬如話去到二零二五年嘅時候咧，如果係延展嘅話咧，能唔能夠達到嗰入場人數係八百至一千萬，同埋係繼續上升？
係誒主席誒，無論係迪士尼樂園同埋海洋公園咧，都面對我哋特別係香港面對嘅獨有情況。我諗，自從舊年嘅社會事件以至到係誒新冠肺炎之後咧，其實大家都知道香港嘅經濟誒嘅動力咧，無可避免咧都要有新。
嘅思維過去沙士誒之後咧，以旅遊業帶動嘅模式咧，大家都明白誒。就算係旅遊業再次復甦咧，估計都唔會好似以前噉係可以再用同一個pattern去去支持香港經濟。咁所以我希望阿局長誒去思考海洋公園嘅。
其實嗰個盈利或者係各方面咧，我覺得都唔算係非常理想嘅。咁何況而家面對一個新嘅境況，咁所以我希望局長即係唔知你呢方面有冇思考，或者已經有一啲諗法啦。我覺得呢個一應該一拼同。
咁所以簡單嚟講，你見到喺隨住過呢兩個禮拜，隨住疫情好轉嘅時候，我哋都爭取及早畀個園樂園係開翻，而且係一個即係喺公眾安全嘅情況之下去做嘅。啊，至於社區站嗰部分，我誒容許我畀翻誒元方去。
時候同樣都要諗下迪士尼。迪士尼其實當時大家都明白佢點樣出世㗎啦，係咪就係因為沙士之後希望誒救香港，噉就揾咗迪士尼嚟。其實已經經歷咗黃金歲月旅遊業嘅黃金歲月，但係迪士尼其實就算喺旅遊業嘅黃金歲月，由於各樣各樣原因咧，其實
海洋公園定位去諗嘅，好多市民都講香港咁細嘅地方，加埋旅遊業面對嘅新挑戰，誒其實好難嘅。再加埋區域嘅競爭啊，好難再支持有兩個園區㗎啦。咁呢個我自己都同意嘅。噉啊誒誒，請阿局長再諗啦。呢個第一點。第二點咧就係我覺得，既然迪士尼。
都係面對呢個挑戰啦，香港人已經做咗呢咁多投資啦。比對起海洋公園咧、迪士尼誒，過去喺誒喺做社會企業責任方面咧，我覺得係唔夠嘅。雖然都係有推出一啲關愛飛啦嚇，經過議員大家努力底下，有啲弱勢社羣。
都進入去，但係我一直都覺得迪士尼係可以好似海洋公園咁咧，畀長者係免費入場嘅係嘛？反正你我哋都要畀錢㗎啦，反正我哋都而家都冇得收回成本，佢樂園都起到，估計人數亦都唔係真係會滿得好似以前噉。其實可唔可以先做呢部分先咧？等啲香港嘅長者都可以。
可以好似海洋公園咁噉，可以係去享受下呢個我哋都投資好多嘅嘅嘅樂園啦。因為事實而家因為海誒迪士尼仲係要收錢咧，都唔係個個長者都都會都會去去過咯，或者家人都係冇咁積極帶啲長者去迪士尼咯。噉我希望阿局長你都可以諗一諗。
噉就誒係先答答咗呢兩點先啦，唔該。好啊。誒，我答第一部分，我第二部分社會站嗰度，我交翻畀元芳去回答。唔該，局長。第一部分誒，我同意阿李慧瓊議員所講嘅就係話，面對誒我哋嗰個旅遊業嘅生態嘅改變咧，其實呢個早喺即係呢兩年裡面咧，我哋已經講㗎。你記得喺前年嘅。
時候我哋推出嗰個即係旅遊發展藍圖嘅時候已經講明啦，我哋唔係追求一個數字上嘅嘅增長，而係必然要即係令到旅遊業本身係對香港帶嚟一個即係經濟社會民生有利嘅情況，亦都要可能即係從質嗰方面去處理，包括咧兩個主題公園或者一啲所謂我哋嘅誒旅遊基建嘅項目。
咧都要即係做得好，咁方向不外乎係幾個。第一個咧就係佢都係需要再投資更新嘅。如果唔係，即係始終呢啲誒設施嚟講咧，如果誒落後咗啊等等，佢未必一定吸引。咁中間亦都涉及推廣同埋營運，而尤其是即係話喺面對即係嗰個誒市場逆轉嘅時候咧，嗰個成
成本開支啊，財務管理係重要嘅。咁所以每一次我哋同元方去討論嘅時候，都有包括呢方面嘅情況。咁所以我哋一方面係審視緊佢即係我哋原先誒計劃咗嘅嗰啲誒長遠嘅投資。第二方面喺嗰個推廣同埋營運方面點樣做。第三方面咧喺成本管理咧係亦都係一個好重要嘅情況。
阿局長同埋各位官員嘅一直。
誒，同我哋充分嘅合作，嚇，多謝。噉啊，多謝主席，多謝。誒，冇其他議程，我宣佈會議結束。多謝大家。
careful thought and decision. We did apply for the ESS program, awaiting for approval. 好嘅，多謝多謝大家委員同埋政府各位官員，因為今日係本屆立法會最後一個誒會議，噉啊多謝。
that helps support the elderly. Those tickets are available to them for free as well. But I think please consider my suggestion. Thank you. Thank you. So one very last question for me, a very simple one. Did you did the dislayland apply for the government employment support scheme?
Stevani, you give the elderly free entrance. Yes, we we actually have a very low price ticket for elderly, one hundred Hong Kong dollars, and that has been the case since the park opened over fifteen years ago. But I would say that our contribution.
back to the local community are different from Ocean Park. As I've mentioned, we are very committed. With over one hundred zero tickets each year that are issued to underprivileged families, our focus is very much on children and providing them with the support and giving them the opportunities to enjoy the experiences in our.
part， we've mentioned a few examples in the report already， but I'll also share that we're very focused on children who are in a palliative state， maybe， or receiving cancer treatments。 very much committed to the Make-A-Wish Foundation around the world， and so we're making sure that
Our contributions back to the community are delivered to families and children who are in need, and that that's been a big focus for us for since the inception, since the beginning of the park. And then we've most recently, of course, with the excess food supply that has come into the park as we were adjusting, giving.
That food supply and we have always contributed through that organisation over many years, the FoodLink program. And so our our food and beverage team and our chefs are very proud of their participation in all of those programs. So these are just a few examples of our commitment to the community, and we very
much feel the obligation as a citizen of of the community that we should contribute. Thank you. Will you consider my suggestion? That is not to charge anything for the elderly. We actually, I know that you have already charged a lower price, but it's different, right? Right, and through our NGO organi
四或五千僱員。It's it's been a very long, challenging year, and much much like the business community here in Hong Kong, throughout tourism, we have had a situation where we felt like keeping our talent and our workforce in place and intact is important. And so, through the